<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Maomao Hu</title>
    <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maomaohu.net/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020 Maomao Hu</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maomaohu.net/images/icon_hu1fba2d0b8dc8bfe246be87df8bc2bbf8_10050_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Python Package - Interpretable Feature Extraction of Electricity Loads (IFEEL)</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We developed a Python package (IFEEL), which aims to help energy data analysts to readily extract interpretable features of daily electricity profiles from a physical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IFEEL Docs can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/software/ifeel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nov 2020 | A talk was given by Dr. Hu at the China-UK Workshop on “Integrating Sustainable Technologies into the Design Strategies of New Communities or Regeneration Projects” funded by NSFC China and the British Council.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk entitled &amp;ldquo;Classification and Characterization of Smart Meter Data Using Interpretable Feature Extraction and Feature-based Clustering&amp;rdquo; was given by Dr. Hu at the China-UK Workshop on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/environmental-design/research-projects/2020/nov/integrating-sustainable-technologies-design-strategies-new-communities-or&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Integrating Sustainable Technologies into the Design Strategies of New Communities or Regeneration Projects”&lt;/a&gt; funded by NSFC China and the British Council Newton Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper published in *Building Simulation*!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our recent research paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Development of an ANN-based Building Energy Model for Information-poor Buildings Using Transfer Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; was published in &lt;em&gt;Building Simulation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full paper can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12273-020-0711-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurate building energy prediction is vital to develop optimal control strategies to enhance building energy efficiency and energy flexibility. In recent years, the data-driven approach based on machine learning algorithms has been widely adopted for building energy prediction due to the availability of massive data in building automation systems (BASs), which automatically collect and store real-time building operational data. For new buildings and most existing buildings without installing advanced BASs, there is a lack of sufficient data to train data-driven predictive models. Transfer learning is a promising method to develop accurate and reliable data-driven building energy prediction models with limited training data by taking advantage of the rich data/knowledge obtained from other buildings. Few studies focused on the influences of source building datasets, pre-training data volume, and training data volume on the performance of the transfer learning method. The present study aims to develop a transfer learning-based ANN model for one-hour ahead building energy prediction to fill this research gap. Around 400 non-residential buildings’ data from the open-source Building Genome Project are used to test the proposed method. Extensive analysis demonstrates that transfer learning can effectively improve the accuracy of BPNN-based building energy models for information-poor buildings with very limited training data. The most influential building features which influence the effectiveness of transfer learning are found to be building usage and industry. The research outcomes can provide guidance for implementation of transfer learning, especially in selecting appropriate source buildings and datasets for developing accurate building energy prediction models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper published in *Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews*!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our recent review article entitled &lt;strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032120305372?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neighborhood-level coordination and negotiation techniques for managing demand-side flexibility in residential microgrids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was published in &lt;em&gt;Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews&lt;/em&gt;. Glad to see my last piece of work at PolyU coming out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The management of demand-side flexibility plays a key role in reliable integration of intermittent renewable energy sources into residential microgrids. Residential microgrid is a dynamic and complex cyber-physical system, which consists of multiple cooperative, non-cooperative and even conflicting entities. Random and separate demand-side management of the multiple entities may have detrimental effects on the grid reliability like the peak “rebound” issue and on the economic benefits for both utilities and consumers. Harmonized coordination, not merely unorganized cooperation, among cooperative entities and negotiation among non-cooperative entities based on information sharing are therefore needed to achieve the neighborhood-level optimal solutions in a residential microgrid. This paper comprehensively reviews the state-of-the-art classification, technologies, architectures, and techniques for neighborhood-level coordination and negotiation in residential microgrids. Various types of coordination and negotiation behaviors are first categorized. The technologies, i.e., demand-side flexible resources involved in coordination and negotiation, are then summarized and introduced, including flexible loads, storage, and distributed generations. The typical architectures for coordination and negotiation are then classified into centralized, decentralized, hierarchical distributed, and non-hierarchical distributed architecture. Last, the major coordination and negotiation techniques, including multi-agent system, optimization and game theory, are reviewed and summarized. The challenges and opportunities for each technique are identified and critically discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New start at University of Oxford!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since March 2020, I joins the Energy and Environmental Informatics group in Department of Engineering Science at University of Oxford. I works with Professor 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eng.ox.ac.uk/people/david-wallom/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Wallom&lt;/a&gt; as a postdoctoral researcher for Project 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amidine.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AMIDiNe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
