<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Maomao Hu</title>
    <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maomaohu.net/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2021 Maomao Hu</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maomaohu.net/images/icon_hu1fba2d0b8dc8bfe246be87df8bc2bbf8_10050_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oct 2021 | Our new paper entitled &#34;Classification and characterization of intra-day load curves of PV and non-PV households using interpretable feature extraction and feature-based clustering&#34; was published in *Sustainable Cities and Society*!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our recent research paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Classification and characterization of intra-day load curves of PV and non-PV households using interpretable feature extraction and feature-based clustering&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; was published in &lt;em&gt;Sustainable Cities and Society&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was financially supported by the UK Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) under the grant (EP/S030131/1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full paper can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2210670721006533&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Load pattern categorization plays a significant role in enhancing the understanding of demand characteristics of different cohorts of energy customers on a distribution network. For a distribution network with embedded photovoltaic (PV) systems, it is also desirable to enumerate these premises since unreported PV installations can have a detrimental impact on voltage control, frequency regulation, and incur reverse power flows. In this paper, a holistic smart meter data analytics approach is proposed for classifying and characterizing the intra-day load curves of PV and non-PV households. Unlike existing studies based on raw time-series data, a series of interpretable and discriminating global and peak-period features are first developed to extract the physical information of load patterns. A two-step feature-based clustering is then applied to classify the load profiles of PV and non-PV households. A post-clustering quantitative compositional analysis is developed to characterize the energy use variability and compositional changes for each household. The proposed PV household identification method allows network owners to identify the existence of PV installations in a particular area for voltage control and ancillary service provision. In the longer term, effective load pattern categorization and post-clustering characterization can help better understand demand characteristics of different cohorts of customers, network utilization, and network-level changes in load growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aug 2021 | A talk was given at the Sino-UK Joint Symposium on Post Covid-19 Pandemic - A Reconsideration for the Built Environment.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk was given at the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sujs2021.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sino-UK Joint Symposium on Post Covid-19 Pandemic - A Reconsideration for the Built Environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, hosted by Tongji University, China and University of Nottingham, UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This symposium  was supported by Researcher Links grant, 2020-RLWK12-10630, under the Newton-China partnership. The grant is funded by the UK Department for Business, Energy and Industrial Strategy and National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) and delivered by the British Council.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aug 2021 | A talk was given to the School of Environmental Science and Engineering, Huangzhong University of Science and Technology.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk was given to the School of Environmental Science and Engineering, Huangzhong University of Science and Technology, China on &amp;ldquo;Data-driven Descriptive, Predictive, and Prescriptive Analytics of Building and Urban Energy Systems&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May 2021 | I am now a participant in IEA EBC 81 and IEA EBC 82 projects.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am glad to share that I am now a participant in two IEA EBC (International Energy Agency, Energy in Buildings and Communities) ongoing projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://annex81.iea-ebc.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IEA ANNEX 81&lt;/strong&gt; Data-Driven Smart Buildings&lt;/a&gt; (2020-2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://annex82.iea-ebc.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IEA ANNEX 82&lt;/strong&gt;  Energy Flexible Buildings Towards Resilient Low Carbon Energy Systems&lt;/a&gt; (2020-2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for having me in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apr 2021 | A talk was given to the Dept. of Built Environment and Enery Application Engineering, Hunan University.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk was given to the Dept. of Built Environment and Enery Application Engineering, Hunan University on &amp;ldquo;Data-driven Descriptive, Predictive, and Prescriptive Analytics of Building and Urban Energy Systems&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jan 2021 | Our R package named PHOVAFER (PHOtoVoltAic FindER) was released.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“PHOtoVoltAic FindER” (phovafer) is developed for identifying the solar photovoltaic (PV) customers among regular customers on a  low-voltage distribution network. It contains the R functions for data representation, feature extraction, and PV users’ classification using the extracted features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PHOVAFER Docs can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/software/phovafer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dec 2020 | Glad to share that I was recently appointed as a Reviewer Board member of the jounal of *Science and Technology for the Built Environment* .</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Dr. Hu was appointed as a member of the Reviewer Board of the journal of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?show=editorialBoard&amp;amp;journalCode=uhvc21&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science and Technology for the Built Environment (STBE)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nov 2020 | A talk was given at the China-UK Workshop on “Integrating Sustainable Technologies into the Design Strategies of New Communities or Regeneration Projects” funded by Newton Fund.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk entitled &amp;ldquo;Classification and Characterization of Smart Meter Data Using Interpretable Feature Extraction and Feature-based Clustering&amp;rdquo; was given by Dr. Hu at the China-UK Workshop on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/environmental-design/research-projects/2020/nov/integrating-sustainable-technologies-design-strategies-new-communities-or&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Integrating Sustainable Technologies into the Design Strategies of New Communities or Regeneration Projects”&lt;/a&gt; funded by NSFC China and the British Council Newton Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oct 2020 | Our Python package named IFEEL (Interpretable Feature Extraction of Electricity Loads) was released.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We developed a Python package (IFEEL), which aims to help energy data analysts to readily extract interpretable features of daily electricity profiles from a physical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IFEEL Docs can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/software/ifeel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sep 2020 | Our new paper entitled &#34;Development of an ANN-based Building Energy Model for Information-poor Buildings Using Transfer Learning&#34; was published in *Building Simulation*!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our recent research paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Development of an ANN-based Building Energy Model for Information-poor Buildings Using Transfer Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; was published in &lt;em&gt;Building Simulation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full paper can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12273-020-0711-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurate building energy prediction is vital to develop optimal control strategies to enhance building energy efficiency and energy flexibility. In recent years, the data-driven approach based on machine learning algorithms has been widely adopted for building energy prediction due to the availability of massive data in building automation systems (BASs), which automatically collect and store real-time building operational data. For new buildings and most existing buildings without installing advanced BASs, there is a lack of sufficient data to train data-driven predictive models. Transfer learning is a promising method to develop accurate and reliable data-driven building energy prediction models with limited training data by taking advantage of the rich data/knowledge obtained from other buildings. Few studies focused on the influences of source building datasets, pre-training data volume, and training data volume on the performance of the transfer learning method. The present study aims to develop a transfer learning-based ANN model for one-hour ahead building energy prediction to fill this research gap. Around 400 non-residential buildings’ data from the open-source Building Genome Project are used to test the proposed method. Extensive analysis demonstrates that transfer learning can effectively improve the accuracy of BPNN-based building energy models for information-poor buildings with very limited training data. The most influential building features which influence the effectiveness of transfer learning are found to be building usage and industry. The research outcomes can provide guidance for implementation of transfer learning, especially in selecting appropriate source buildings and datasets for developing accurate building energy prediction models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aug 2020 | Our new paper entitled &#34;Neighborhood-level Coordination and Negotiation Techniques for Managing Demand-side Flexibility in Residential Microgrids&#34; was published in *Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews*.</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our recent review article entitled &lt;strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032120305372?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neighborhood-level coordination and negotiation techniques for managing demand-side flexibility in residential microgrids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was published in &lt;em&gt;Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews&lt;/em&gt;. Glad to see my last piece of work at PolyU coming out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The management of demand-side flexibility plays a key role in reliable integration of intermittent renewable energy sources into residential microgrids. Residential microgrid is a dynamic and complex cyber-physical system, which consists of multiple cooperative, non-cooperative and even conflicting entities. Random and separate demand-side management of the multiple entities may have detrimental effects on the grid reliability like the peak “rebound” issue and on the economic benefits for both utilities and consumers. Harmonized coordination, not merely unorganized cooperation, among cooperative entities and negotiation among non-cooperative entities based on information sharing are therefore needed to achieve the neighborhood-level optimal solutions in a residential microgrid. This paper comprehensively reviews the state-of-the-art classification, technologies, architectures, and techniques for neighborhood-level coordination and negotiation in residential microgrids. Various types of coordination and negotiation behaviors are first categorized. The technologies, i.e., demand-side flexible resources involved in coordination and negotiation, are then summarized and introduced, including flexible loads, storage, and distributed generations. The typical architectures for coordination and negotiation are then classified into centralized, decentralized, hierarchical distributed, and non-hierarchical distributed architecture. Last, the major coordination and negotiation techniques, including multi-agent system, optimization and game theory, are reviewed and summarized. The challenges and opportunities for each technique are identified and critically discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mar 2020 | New journey in Dept. of Engineering Science at University of Oxford!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since March 2020, I joins the Energy and Environmental Informatics group in Department of Engineering Science at University of Oxford. I works with Professor 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eng.ox.ac.uk/people/david-wallom/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Wallom&lt;/a&gt; as a postdoctoral researcher for Project 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amidine.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AMIDiNe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
