<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Maomao Hu</title>
    <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maomaohu.net/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020 Maomao Hu</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maomaohu.net/images/icon_hu1fba2d0b8dc8bfe246be87df8bc2bbf8_10050_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper published in *Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews*!</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/post/post_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to share that our recent review article &lt;strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032120305372?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neighborhood-level coordination and negotiation techniques for managing demand-side flexibility in residential microgrids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was published in &lt;em&gt;Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews&lt;/em&gt;. Glad to see my last piece of work at PolyU coming out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residential microgrid is a dynamic and complex cyber-physical system, which consists of multiple cooperative, non-cooperative and even conflicting entities. Harmonised coordination, not merely unorganised cooperation, among cooperative entities and negotiation among non-cooperative entities based on information sharing are needed to achieve the neighbourhood-level optimal solutions in a residential microgrid. Typical architectures for coordination and negotiation are classified into centralised, decentralised, hierarchical distributed, and non-hierarchical distributed architecture. Major coordination and negotiation techniques, including multi-agent system, optimisation and game theory, are reviewed and summarised.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
