<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MPC | Maomao Hu | National University of Singapore</title>
    <link>https://maomaohu.net/tag/mpc/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maomaohu.net/tag/mpc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>MPC</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2025 BIOR Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maomaohu.net/images/logo.svg</url>
      <title>MPC</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/tag/mpc/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MPC of Variable-speed ACs for Demand Response in Smart Grids</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/project/0_mpc_ac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/project/0_mpc_ac/</guid>
      <description>




  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-schematic-diagram-of-mpc-for-building-energy-systems&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/0_mpc_ac/2_hu4e3e9b67fd1f8a1eb8ef5d4a8814a019_1068216_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig. Schematic diagram of MPC for building energy systems.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/0_mpc_ac/2_hu4e3e9b67fd1f8a1eb8ef5d4a8814a019_1068216_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;4211&#34; height=&#34;1764&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig. Schematic diagram of MPC for building energy systems.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;#B30606&#34;&gt;Demo Video: How MPC works?&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;












  


&lt;video controls &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;MPC_video.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;font face=&#34;Roboto&#34; color=&#34;black&#34; size=&#34;4&#34;&gt;Receding Horizon Optimization: Optimization&amp;rarr;Decision&amp;rarr;Measurement&amp;rarr;Optimization&amp;rarr;Decision&amp;rarr;Measurement ...&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;#B30606&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of smart grids, residential air conditioners, as the major contributors to home electricity bills and loads on electrical grids, need to be not only energy-efficient, but also grid-responsive to relieve power supply-demand imbalance. Existing demand response control strategies for residential air conditioners focus on single-speed type and mainly adopt temperature set point reset to respond to hourly day-ahead electricity prices. This study represents the first attempt to directly control the operating frequency of inverter air conditioners in response to high-granularity electricity price signals, i.e., 5-minute real-time electricity prices, using model predictive control method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simplified room thermal model in the stochastic state-space representation and performance maps of an inverter air conditioner are developed and integrated for predicting the coupled thermal response of an air-conditioned room. A demand response-enabled model predictive controller is designed based on the coupled model to optimally control the operating frequency of the inverter air conditioner while taking account of all the influential variables including weather conditions, occupancy, and 5-min real-time electricity prices. A Kalman filter is adopted to estimate the unmeasurable variables and remove the noises in measurements. A TRNSYS-MATLAB co-simulation testbed is developed to test the thermal and energy performances of the model predictive controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results show that compared to the PID controller, the demand response-enabled model predictive controller can implement automatic and optimal precooling to improve occupant’s thermal comfort at the beginning of occupancy. Moreover, it can also reduce average power consumption during peak demand periods by 17.31% to 38.86% compared with the PID controller and reduce all-day electricity costs by 0.42% to 22.16%. The frequency-based model predictive control method enables residential inverter air conditioners to be more grid-friendly and cost-efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Publication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/publication/j5/&#34;&gt;Maomao Hu, Fu Xiao, John Bagterp Jørgensen, Shengwei Wang (2019). Frequency control of air conditioners in response to real-time dynamic electricity prices in smart grids. Applied Energy.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/publication/c3/&#34;&gt;Maomao Hu, Fu Xiao (2018). Model Predictive Control of Inverter Air Conditioners Responding to Real-Time Electricity Prices in Smart Grids. 5th International High Performance Buildings Conference.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MPC of Floor Heating Systems in Denmark</title>
      <link>https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/</guid>
      <description>




  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-schematic-of-the-grey-box-rc-model-for-floor-heating-systems&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/RC_floor_hu05495c42067aabfcf0155ad9aca991df_263899_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig. Schematic of the grey-box RC model for floor heating systems&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/RC_floor_hu05495c42067aabfcf0155ad9aca991df_263899_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2379&#34; height=&#34;1871&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig. Schematic of the grey-box RC model for floor heating systems
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-flow-chart-of-online-model-predictive-control-for-floor-heating-systems&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/MPC_scheme_hua67dd61a10cfbd2f196b5f3ce34c174c_407573_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig. Flow chart of online model predictive control for floor heating systems.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/project/1_mpc_floor/MPC_scheme_hua67dd61a10cfbd2f196b5f3ce34c174c_407573_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2304&#34; height=&#34;2104&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig. Flow chart of online model predictive control for floor heating systems.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Floor heating (FH) system is a widely-used thermally active building system, which can take advantage of building thermal mass to shift energy demands to off-peak hours. Its ability of effective  utilization of low-temperature energy resources also helps to increase energy efficiency and reduce greenhouse gas emissions. However, control of FH systems remains a challenge due to the large thermal inertia of the pipe-embedded concrete floor. In the context of smart grids, the control issue becomes more complicated because the dynamic electricity prices need to be taken into consideration to achieve economic benefits and encourage demand response participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, an advanced optimal control method, i.e., model predictive control (MPC), is developed for FH systems, which can simultaneously consider all the influential variables including weather conditions, occupancy and dynamic electricity prices. Considering the on-line computational efficiency, a control-oriented dynamic thermal model for a room integrated with FH system is developed and represented in a stochastic state-space form. An economic MPC controller, formulated as a mixed integer linear programming problem, is designed for FH systems. A TRNSYS-MATLAB co-simulation testbed is developed to test and compare different control methods under various operating conditions in terms of energy consumption, thermal comfort and operating costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test results show that, compared to the conventional on-off controller, the MPC controller is able to use building thermal mass to optimally shift energy consumption to low-price periods, improve thermal comfort at the beginning of occupancy, reduce energy demand during peak periods, and save electricity costs for residential end-users. The weather conditions and electricity prices have influences on the start-up time and duration of preheating, energy flexibility potential and electricity cost savings of FH systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presented work receives the support of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://smart-cities-centre.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CITIES project&lt;/a&gt;, the SCA project, and the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energylabnordhavn.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EnergyLab Nordhavn project&lt;/a&gt; in Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Publication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://maomaohu.net/publication/j4/&#34;&gt;Maomao Hu, Fu Xiao, John Bagterp Jørgensen, Rongling Li (2019). Price-responsive model predictive control of floor heating systems for demand response using building thermal mass. Applied Thermal Engineering.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
